原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/ayYgPdk0VVc
原视频发布日期：20200705
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
你好 我是Scott Manley
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
今天火箭实验室的电子火箭在第13次发射中出现了故障
Today at Rocket Lab's Electron rocket suffered a failure in flight on its 13th launch.
大约在发射后5分30秒
It was about 5 minutes 30 seconds into flight
视频画面没了 但遥测信号仍在持续接收
when video gave out but telemetry kept going.
那么这次发射被称为无图无真相
So the launch was named Pics or it didn't happen
我们真的是在入轨前丢了视频信号 从而未能入轨
and we literally lost the video feed before it made it into orbit.
所以(入轨这事儿)它没有发生
So it didn't happen.
那么这个名字是参考了它的主要有效载荷
Now the name was a reference to the primary payload.
它是佳能电子公司的CE-SAT 1B
It was Canon Electronics CE-SAT 1B.
那是一颗成像卫星(光学遥感卫星) 他们计划将许多这样的卫星发射到太空
It was an imaging satellite and they're actually planning to launch many of these into space.
佳能实际上参与了他们自己的小型运载火箭的开发 叫做太空一号
And Canon are actually involved in the development of their own small launch vehicle called Space One.
这并不是唯一的有效载荷
It wasn't the only payload.
还有一些来自行星实验室的较小的立方星 一些超级鸽子
There was also a number of smaller cube SATs from Planet Labs, a number of SuperDoves.
因为这些鸽子是3U立方体星
If you know the the doves are 3U CubeSats
其中有差不多百毫米光圈的相机 用来拍摄地球的图像
which have like a hundred millimeter aperture camera that they used to image the earth.
而超级指的是新版本
And the Super refers to the new versions
1.8Gbps下行无线电，飞掠每个地面站时有85GB的数据传输能力，4核1.6GHz处理器，2TB星上存储，
80瓦时电池容量，50瓦峰值发电功率，4700万像素相机，35km幅宽
它们的成像传感器可以覆盖更多的频段
which have many many more frequency bands that they can cover with their imaging sensors.
所有这些卫星都将被发射到两极上空的500公里的太阳同步轨道上
All of these satellites were going to be launched into a 500 kilometer Sun Synchronous Orbit over the poles.
那么发射将从新西兰的火箭实验室的设施中进行
So the launch was gonna be from Rocket Labs facility from New Zealand.
火箭实验室实际上将发射时间提前了一天 试图挤出时间来发射
And they'd actually brought it forward by one day to try and squeeze out a launch
这样才能避开之后一系列会拖延发射的恶劣天气
before the an extended patch of bad weather was gonna ruin their day and keep them on the ground.
起初 火箭的第一级准时升空
Initially the rocket looked like it was going fighting the first stage ascended on time.
有一个贴纸 在快要分级(一二级分离)前被剥开
There was a decal that began to peel off just prior to staging
但我不觉得这会与失败有关
but I don't think anybody thinks that's relevant to the failure.
一二级分离正常
Staging looked clean.
二级点火了
The second stage kicked in
并在接下来的几分钟内将火箭的速度提升到3.8km/s的速度
and that boosted the rocket over the next couple of minutes to a speed of 3.8 kilometers per second
这时 视频信号丢失了
and that was when the video signal was lost.
但遥测(信号)仍在继续
but the telemetry did continue.
现在遥测显示没有加速度
Now the telemetry showed no acceleration
而火箭在数秒内减速 之后高度停止了增加
and the Rockets slows slightly for a number of seconds until the altitude stopped increasing
然后高度开始下降 速度开始上升
and then the altitude started decreasing and the velocity started increasing.
最大达到了194.8km的高度
It reached a peak altitude of 194.8 kilometers
总体来讲也许该相信这个遥测数据 因为(直播)主持人非常明确地提到视频信号的丢失
and the whole we can probably trust this telemetry because the host very specifically mentions losing video
但遥测数据仍在传递
but the telemetry was still being delivered.
所以这就是为什么我相信这些数字
So that's why I'm trusting these numbers.
是根据主持人的说法
It based on this.
它落回了大气层
It fell back into the atmosphere.
火箭飞行了不到一千公里
The vehicle traveled less than a thousand kilometers.
它可能在再入的火球中解体
It probably broke up in a fireball
而你可能会说那是庆祝烟火的红光(?) 因为至少对美国时区那时是7月4日
and you might say that's the Rockets red glare because it was the fourth of July at least in US time zone.
所以自从那次失败后 火箭实验室和Peter Beck本人都有过几次声明
So since that failure, there have been couple of statements from Rocket Lab and from Peter Beck himself,
确认损失 并为失去这些有效载荷的客户道歉
confirming the loss and apologizing to customers for losing those pay loads
但一直没有多余的线索
but there's been no extra clues.
虽然声明的文字很奇怪地谈到了4分钟时的失败
Although the text of the statement curiously talks about a failure at four minutes in,
而不是5分40秒
rather than five minutes and 40 seconds.
所以 这要么是透露出在5分钟之前事情就出了问题 要么就是他们只是犯了一个错误
So this is either revealing that things were going wrong before the five minutes or that they just made a mistake.
在我们看到出事儿之前 任务控制的音频并没有表明内部有什么问题
Mission control audio didn't suggest the inner thing was wrong until after we saw things going wrong.
所以 就目前而言 我们并没有太多的线索 但我们还是来谈谈我们所知的东西
So as of right now we don't have a lot to go on but let's talk about what we do know.
那么 复习一下电子火箭
So, a refresher on Electron,
它是一种小型火箭 加满推进剂后质量约为10吨
it's a small rocket which masses about ten tons when fully fueled with propellant.
它由碳纤维复合材料制成 由卢瑟福发动机推动
It's constructed from carbon fiber composite and it's propelled by the Rutherford engines
燃烧RP1煤油和液氧的小型电动(燃料)泵发动机
which are small electrically pumped engines burning RP1 and liquid oxygen
Astra也是电泵但是还没入轨过
也是目前唯一使用电泵引擎的(入轨)火箭
and it's the only rocket flying right now that uses electrically pumped engines
部分原因是对于小型发动机 涡轮泵的效率较低
partly because for small engines the turbo pumps become less efficient
而电动发动机变得更容易
and the electrical engines become easier.
所以第一阶段有九个这样的小型发动机和电池组
So the first stage has nine of these small engines and the battery pack
它能够提供一兆瓦的功率 为这些东西提供动力
which is able to deliver one megawatt of power for powering these things.
第二阶段只使用一台卢瑟福发动机
The second stage only uses a single Rutherford engine
与一个大的真空优化的喷嘴和较小的电池组
with a large vacuum optimized nozzle and smaller battery pack.
第二级实际上有三块电池 最初只有两块电池为发动机提供动力
The second stage actually has three batteries and initially only two of the battery's power the engine
但随着电量的耗尽 发动机会进行热插拔 这是他们自己的术语
but as these get depleted, the engine does a hot swap that's their own terminology
(在发动机运行时)换上第三块电池 丢掉两块死电池
to switch in the third battery and drop the two dead batteries
然后它们从火箭上掉下来 以减少第二级的质量
and then they literally get dropped off the rocket to reduce the mass of the second stage
而这是计划在飞行6分20秒后进行的
and this is scheduled for 6 minutes and 20 seconds into the flight
可那是在我们看到故障的时间点往后40秒左右
but that was about 40 seconds after we saw the failure.
所以再仔细看看视频
So looking closely at the video.
我们可以看到一些东西 一些线索 就在视频停止之前
There's a few things we can see, a few clues, just before the video stops.
许多人都发现了 发动机喷嘴的红光消失了一点
It looks to me and many others like the red glow of the engine nozzle fades a bit.
现在很难确定这一点
Now it's hard to be sure about this
因为在飞行过程中 发动机的光芒(本身就不稳定) 会四处移动
because the engine glow kind of moves around during the flight anyway.
但是 如果我们打开洗脑循环
But if we take a loop and we bounce it back and forth.
很明显 它正在逐渐消失
It is really obvious that this is sort of fading away.
其次 如果你像我一样把遥测数据拿出来的话
Now secondly, if you take the telemetry it like I did
画图找出加速度或速度与时间的关系
and you plot a graph to find the acceleration or the velocity versus time
并由此可以计算出加速度
and that from that you can figure out the acceleration.
或者说 在故障前的几秒内
Or the seconds leading up towards the failure.
加速度大致恒定在1.3G左右
The acceleration is more or less constant at around 1.3 G
但随后它实际上下降了约20％并维持了几秒钟 然后迅速下降到零
but then it actually drops by about 20% for a couple of seconds before crashing down to zero
而这也许说明有些东西在逐渐出问题 然后真出问题了
and maybe that's a sign that something is progressively going wrong and then really going wrong.
在失去联系的同时 火箭的姿态也出现了变化
There also appears to be a change in the vehicle attitude just as the contact is lost.
这可能是飞行计划的一部分
And this might be part of the flight plan
或者它可能只是正常的随机晃动 因为视频切出来了才看起来很糟糕
or it might be just normal random wobble that looks bad because the video cuts out.
但也可能是姿态的重大失控
But it could also be a significant loss of attitude control.
任务控制中心的报告显示电池的电力是正常的
The Mission Control call-outs suggest that the electrical power from the batteries is nominal
正如我所说的那样 他们正在为热插拔做准备
as I mean they're getting ready for the hot swap.
关于热插拔是如何在航天器上进行的 有一些疑问
There is some question actually about how the hot swap happens on the spacecraft
比如电池真的是一瞬间切换的吗
whether they literally just switch over from one bank to the other instantaneously
或者说 如果随着两块电池的耗尽 能够提供的电量越来越少
or if as the two batteries get depleted and are able to deliver less and less power,
也许是另一块电池被换了一部分 以弥补一些不足
maybe it's the other battery gets swapped in partially to make up some of the shortfall.
我们对这套系统的了解还不够多
We don't really know enough about this system
但越是复杂 就越有可能涉及到某种故障
but the more complex that is the more likely it could be involved in some sort of failure.
所以在我看来
So look it looks to me like.
这是一个发动机故障
This is an engine failure.
先是推力下降 之后推力消失
We get the reduced thrust and then we get no thrust.
喷嘴温度下降
We get the nozzle cooling.
之后我们就得问问为什么视频信号会比遥测信号先丢失
And you know then we have to ask why with the video feed drop but not the telemetry feed.
我不认为这是一个暴力的故障 比如发生了爆炸破坏了相机或者储罐或者其他东西
I don't think this is a violent failure that blew away the camera or destroy the tank or anything
因为如果是这样
because if that were the case
我想 随着加压气体的逸出 你会看到遥测数据的变化会更剧烈
I think you would see a bigger change to the telemetry as pressurized gas escapes.
然而 遥测数据有可能是通过更全向的天线传递下来的
However it is possible the telemetry is coming down over a more omnidirectional antenna
而视频信号则是通过更需要指向性的天线
whereas the video comes down on a more directional system
那几秒钟的数据 显示了航天器的旋转情况
and that was a few seconds of data showing the rotation of the spacecraft
可能在那之后还在继续 这可能是一种迹象 即
might have just continued after that and this might be an indication that
飞船开始旋转 失去了姿态控制 无法发送视频
the spacecraft started spinning, lost attitude control and was unable to send the video.
是的 我觉得这是完全可能的
Yeah I mean that that's that's totally possible.
也有可能是电力系统出了问题
It's also possible that there's something happening with the electrical system.
你知道 如果一个电池脱落
You know if one of the batteries fell off.
不一定是电池从火箭上掉落下来，也可能是从总线上脱落了
它出于某种原因从总线上脱落了
You know fell off the bus for some reason.
也许第二块电池试图为发动机提供动力 但它不能提供所有需要的动力
Maybe the second battery is trying to power the engine and it can't deliver all the power needed.
所以它只能提供80%的推力
So it's only delivering 80% thrust
然后因为功率太高而失败了
and then because it's working too hard, it then fails.
这也是一种可能 或者说和热插拔有点关系吧
That's a possibility or maybe there's something to do with the hot-swap changeover
也就是第三块电池换进去后就出问题了
where the third battery gets changed in and then something goes wrong.
说实话 我觉得这和热插拔没有什么关系
Honestly I don't think it's anything to do with the hot-swap
但我也做好了相应的推测 因为我很好奇
but I'm prepared to be surprised because I always like to know more.
是的 从现在起 火箭实验室将不得不与联邦航空局合作 以追查事故的原因
And yeah as of right now Rocket Lab will have to work with the FAA to trace the cause of this
也许之后我们会得到一些解答
and maybe we'll get some answers later.
他们确实有另一枚火箭几乎准备好发射了 我预计那枚将被推迟
They did have another rocket practically ready to go and I expect that flight will be delayed.
在他们掌握13号幸运数字的发射问题之前 它将被停飞
It'll be grounded until they have a handle on what the problem might be for number lucky number 13.
正如我以前所说 火箭工程是严苛的
And you know I've said this before rocket engineering is unforgiving
火箭或者链条上的一个小问题可能会导致整个任务失败
and one small problem with your vehicle your chain can kill your entire mission
所以你需要确保一切都完美运行
so you need to make sure everything is working perfectly.
无论如何 只要得到了更多的消息  我肯定会让你们知道
Anyway as soon as we find out more, I'll be sure to let you guys know.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.